and um Rudy uh let's talk about the side
effects of those
glp1 so that is a a very hot subject to
talk about because like everything
nothing comes without side effects so
most of the side effects of glp1 that we
talk about are the short-term side
effects because one of the main things
that gp1s do it delays gastric en
decreases your your rate of digestion so
you get that full that satiety feeling
and you don't eat as much but because of
that GI symptoms like indigestion
constipation nausea sometimes vomiting
can happen but when done properly if
you're eating the right Foods you don't
overeat you don't eat fatty foods you
avoid alcohol as much as possible in
most cases that can be um mitigated or
avoided and then so you know there
there's a great saying in the US where
they say don't throw the baby with the
bath water
right so although some things have side
effects there is a good way that we can
use those tools and mitigate the side
effects so especially when I use the
newer gp1 teal zepeti has way fewer side
effects in in my experience and in
studies also versus seago so my my
strategy to help my patients I tend to
use te zepeti more I always start slow
and I try to micro do and I'm very big
on lifesty style and behavior and
nutrition support to help my patients do
the right thing and while we're doing
this it's not how quickly just how
quickly you lose the weight it's how
quickly can you change your bad habits
and establish new habits so now let's
talk about the long-term the possible
long-term side effects of gb1 and one of
the things that have been in the news
recently is the possibility of the
vision loss that you can see with gp1 so
there was a recent article in Jama
oftalmology where neuro ofal ologist
started doing a report and they found
nine cases of what is
called
nonic
um non alteric ischemic optic neuropathy
which is which can be vision changes
even vision loss that can occur um
they're not sure what it is but it's
usually a decrease of blood flow to the
optic nerve and they've seen nine cases
those were an association not a cation
so they said there were nine cases of
patients um I think they looked at
245,000 medical records and they they
see nine cases and this are those
patients at some point took glp1 so
there's a question mark whether glp1 can
increase that risk there was another
registry of patient of glp1 and that was
done in Europe where they did not see
that Association so the conclusion of
that concl the that joural Jama
oftalmology study was we need to look at
this I'm going to tell you in all my my
career that 20 years I've had maybe
three or four patients who reported
visual changes those were mostly on
mostly on diabetic patients and diabetic
patients know that when their blood
sugars fluctuate usually their Vision
becomes blurry so if I have a patient
that reports to me that they have Vision
issues or blurriness I will send them to
get a dilated eye exam which you should
do every year anyway so out of those
nine cases and remember there's hundreds
of Millions of people taking glp1 now it
is estimated that about 14% of the
population in the US is taking a gp1 to
me that's an underestimation has to be
way more than this and you don't see a
lot of case reports and interestingly
other diseases that were other
medications that have been associated
with that nonon that ischemic optic
nerve
neuropathy uh pde5 Inhibitors things
like Cala and Calis and Viagra I
remember very well three years ago there
was study that did the same thing it
showed that there may be an association
with Viagra and seales with vision
changes and it was Panic even the
lawyers started saying oh maybe we can
get some lawsuits there it was again an
association another medication that can
be associated with this Vision L esic
optic nerve neuropathy is um intranasal
Vel constrictors things that you use to
to alleviate your nasal congestion they
have been reports of association with
visual trouble so it's not just glp1
there are so many things that can cause
that so what I'm doing in my practice
the overwhelming studies are showing
positive results long term the visual um
issue is something we're going to keep
an eye on we're going to follow those
nine Patients Out of the hundred of
millions utilizing this I tell my
patients that if you have any visual
issues to make sure you give me a call
another issue is the possibility of
thyroid cancer with gp1 and that's a big
one because there's still a blackbox
warning on glp1 that it may increase the
risk of a very rare form of to of
thyroid cancer called medular thyroid
carcinoma it's an extremely rare cancer
same thing there was a recent report um
of and those reports are retrospective
study they just look at large database
they see patients who've taken glp1 and
they've seen if they an association with
any kind of of for example thyroid
cancer so there was one study that that
showed that there was an increase up to
58% of that that very rare cancer to
increase in patients during glp1 but
then there was another study that was
done before that where they looked at
almost
250,000 medical records of people taking
glp1 and they did not see an increase in
thyroid cancer so the jurry is still out
and we think that now that patients are
taking glp1 they're going do more
thyroid ultrasounds and we're doing more
biopsies and we're finding more thyroid
cancer because they may have been there
from the beginning there's more of an
emphasis in diagnosing them thyroid
cancer remains a very rare type of
cancer that's very treatable um so the
Jerry is still out on how what is the
risk of thyroid cancer with glp1 and and
what I tell to really a lot of the
detractors is where were those
discussions in 2010 2012 2015 where I
was using glp1 on my patients for years
and there were never those questions so
20 years of experience and we've never
seen that there there's a significant
increase in those issues but that same
study that looked at this also saw that
there was a decrease in 42 different
conditions with the use of grp1 things
like Alzheimer's disease or neurod
degenerative disease decrease almost by
40% we already know that uh with the um
select trial that made gp1 became FD
approved to decrease heart disease that
there's a 20% decrease in cardiovascular
disease major adverse cardiovascular
events with glp1 so let me do a little
exercise with you right now Stephen so
in the USA there's about
700,000 deaths that are attributed to
cardiac disease every year and if we
apply that select trial which was a
really really well-designed trial double
Placebo control trial that show 20%
reduction of death so if there are
700,000 deaths a year and you would put
all of those patients on glp1 you would
save 140,000 lives a year again this is
an oversimplification of Health but if
those patients who are at high risk for
heart disease were taking gp1 we would
see a significant ific Improvement in
their health and decreasing
cardiovascular morbidity and mortality
now could those patients out of those
140,000 deaths that we saved could there
be one or two cases of uptic neuropathy
we don't know because again optic
neuropathy has been associated with all
kinds of other medications so I'm going
to air in the side of we need to treat
metabolic disease and if you need a glp1
you should not be afraid of it because
we have all these years of of of safety
studies and all the benefits that it can
have we talked about this recently that
zeep bound which is the brand name for
Te zepeti has been recently approved for
treatment of obstructive sleep apnea not
only because you lose a lot of weight
with it but they see that it decreases
inflammation especially redundant tissue
around the neck and the nose and
improves um sleep apnea you have less
apnic episodes sleep apnea is strongly
associated with with high blood pressure
and cardiovascular disease so another
indication another benefit I see of glp1
is for the the Improvement of metabolic
associated liver disease fatty liver
this is an epidemic that we're not
talking about about 20 to 30% of
patients have fatty liver disease and
this of course obesity is a big risk
factor but I'm seeing a lot of patients
who are slim quote unquote nor BMI also
with non-alcoholic associated liver
disease that is called now metabolic
associated liver disease so there is an
issue with metabolic disease and having
that tool of glp1 and possibly
testosterone plus glp1 to improve this
is a pathway that should be celebrated
it should be celebrated I'll still
remember again I'm going to say how old
I am in the early 1990s when
we started using ACE inhibitors so we
discovered the pathway PA pathway of ACE
inhibitors medication like lyso and
Ramil to control blood pressure and
decrease cardiovascular risk it was a
revolution in cardiovascular medicine
because before we had mostly better
blockers and calcium channel blockers
once we discovered the pathway of ace
inhibitor we saved so many lives with it
were there side effects associated with
lyso and Ramil of course and those have
way higher risk risk of side effects but
since that time they refined the
molecule the pathway of the ACE
inhibitors was a successful Discovery
for cardiovascular disease I would like
the medical community to look at the
glp1 pathway as a success that we found
that glp1 doesn't just affect the
stomach and the digestion it works on
our brain it's a medication that can
help with addiction and help decrease
the neuroinflammation and the abnormal
Pathways that we see because I describ
something Stephen that patients who deal
with metabolic issue or weight issues
they have a disregulation of appetite
physiology that's a mouthful appetite
physiology is complicated we don't
understand it exactly it's a combination
of grin leptin um sensation of stretch
signals from the stomach the reward
center the dopamine centers in the brain
all of this is involved to really help
control appetite well we just found that
glp1 is a really important pathway for
satiety and for metabolism so we are in
the infancy of gp1 it's only been 20
years so imagine what's going to come in
the future for glp1 we're going to keep
refining it and we're going to find ways
to help with this because we have to
realize that patients who cannot lose
weight it's not because they don't have
willpower it's because they have a
disregulated appetite phys physiology
they know what they should do they can't
get there if we can provide them tools
to help them get there then help them
adopt new habits this is the role of a
physician or or provider to help their
patients